University of Connecticut 1998.0086
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
University of Connecticut, School of Insurance Records
undated, 1937-1969.
1998.0086
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
1.0 Linear feet
In 1936, the School established a Department of Insurance that was incorporated as the Hartford College of Insurance by the Connecticut General Assembly in 1939. In 1943, the Connecticut General Assembly authorized a five-year lease of the Hartford College of Law and Insurance, located at 39 Woodland Street in Hartford, to the University of Connecticut. The collection contains fliers, brochures, course related materials and brief historical details pertaining to the Hartford College of Insurance and the subsequent integration of its programs into those of the University of Connecticut.
University of Connecticut, School of Insurance.
History
The Hartford College of Law was founded in 1921 and approved by the American Bar Association and accredited by the Examining Committee of the Connecticut Bar Association in 1933. In 1936, the School established a Department of Insurance that was incorporated as the Hartford College of Insurance by the Connecticut General Assembly in 1939. Following a decline in day school enrollment during World War II, the Trustees of the Colleges of Law and Insurance looked to the state university to provide long term stability. In 1943, the Connecticut General Assembly authorized a five-year lease of the Hartford College of Law and Insurance, located at 39 Woodland Street in Hartford, to the University of Connecticut. The first Dean was Laurence J. Ackerman (1943-1963) who was succeeded by Robert O. Harvey. On 1 September 1948, the Board of Trustees conveyed full title of the Colleges to the University of Connecticut. By 1946, 154 veterans were enrolled in the Law, Insurance and Pharmacy Schools at the University.
In 1961, the Hartford College of Insurance of the University of Connecticut changed its name to the University of Connecticut School of Insurance. By 1967, the School offered five distinct programs: Bachelor of Science in Insurance Administration; Actuarial science program (begun in July 1966); professional designation programs, including Chartered Property Casualty Underwriting (C.P.C.U), Insurance Institue of America programs in general insurance and education programs for adjusters and risk managers; certificate program; and State of Connecticut Insurance License preparation program. The School also sponsored the Interantional Business Machines Corporation ( IBM Advanced Insurance Industry School beginning in 1960.
Additional information concerning the University of Connecticut School of Law may be found in the School of Law Archives.
Scope and Content
The collection contains fliers, brochures, course related materials and brief historical details pertaining to the Hartford College of Insurance and the subsequent integration of its programs into those of the University of Connecticut.
Arrangement
Series I: Subject Files ( undated, 1937-1969 ) is arranged alphabetically by topic.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University's history. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Unknown.
Hartford College of Insurance.; Insurance Institute of Hartford.; Administrative Records.; Correspondence.; Examinations.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Hartford, Conn.; Photographs.; Publications.
- Series I: Subject Files, undated, 1937-1969
  - Applications for 1941-1942, A - H, 1939 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Applications for 1941-1942, K - R, 1939 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Applications for 1941-1942, S - Y, 1939 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Biographies, undated (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Brochures, undated (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - C.P.C.U. Exam attempts, 1963 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Course Materials, undated (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Course Offerings, undated, 1942-1948, 1967 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Course: Property and Casualty Insurance, 1961 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Flyers, undated (Box 2:, Folder 11)
  - Forms, undated, 1965, 1969 (Box 2:, Folder 12)
  - Hartford College of Insurance, undated, 1939-1941 (Box 2:, Folder 13)
  - IBM Advanced Industry School course
    - Applications, undated (Box 2:, Folder 14)
    - Examinations, quizes and questions, undated (Box 2:, Folder 15)
    - Participants, undated, 1961-1965 (Box 2:, Folder 16)
    - Syllabi, evaluations, descrptions, undated, 1961-1965 (Box 2:, Folder 17)
  - Insurance Institute of Hartford, 1937-1941 (Box 2:, Folder 18)
  - Regional affairs, undated, 1964, 1968 (Box 2:, Folder 19)
  - Underwriter's report, undated (Box 2:, Folder 20)
  - University of Hartford, 1968 (Box 2:, Folder 21)
  - Workstudy Program - Phoenix, undated (Box 2:, Folder 22)